Malware is a broad term that describes
many different types of malicious
software. Although there are many
different types of malware, they are all
still considered to be things that you
do not want to run on your computer.
Some of this malware is designed to
gather information from your system,
such as the keys that you type into your
keyboard. Or maybe this malware is
working together with other systems that
are infected to create a large bot of
systems. Malware could just be showing
you advertising on the screen, which
ultimately makes the attacker some
money. Or you might have viruses, worms,
or other types of malicious software
that are designed to attack your system
and your documents.
In this video, we'll look at many
different types of malware. But keep in
mind that this malware may use multiple
methods to gain access to your system.
One common way is to start with a
vulnerability. This is a known or
unknown issue with your software that
would allow someone access to your
system without the proper credentials.
Once this vulnerability is found, the
malware then begins to embed itself into
your operating system and begin
installing additional software such as a
remote access backdoor. Once that
backdoor software is in place, the
attacker can now connect to your
computer at any time and install new
software, delete files, or modify
information on your computer. For this
malware to get onto your system, there
has to be something that starts this
process. We have to run some type of
malicious software in the memory of your
computer. This might be a malicious link
inside of an email message that connects
you to a website, downloads the
malicious software, and runs it. Or it
might be a popup on a website that
encourages you to click the link. In
reality, it is downloading and
installing malware. Or it could be what
we call a driveby download where you're
simply visiting a website and then it
automatically downloads a file to your
computer. And sometimes it's not
something that you actively do, but
instead it's part of a worm that finds
its way onto your computer without any
type of human intervention. Fortunately,
worms are very rare. So most of the time
we will need to protect oursel by
following the best practices. But it's
always a good idea to keep your
operating system updated to avoid any
vulnerabilities on your system. So, make
sure you run the Windows updater to keep
everything up to date inside of Windows
and make sure that you check all of the
applications on your system so that
they're up todate as well.
One type of popular malware is a Trojan
horse. This is named after the story
behind the Greeks using a large wooden
horse to gain access to the city of
Troy. You are effectively inviting the
software onto your computer and running
it thinking that it's going to provide
you with some type of service or
function, but in reality behind the
scenes, it's malicious software that is
embedding itself into your operating
system. Very often, the anti virus and
anti-malware software you run on your
computer can identify a Trojan horse and
stop it before it becomes embedded onto
your computer. Since you are installing
this Trojan horse with your rights and
your permissions, the Trojan horse now
has access to all of the data and all of
the resources that you do. This is why
it's always a best practice to only
install software that you trust so that
you can avoid any instances of a Trojan
horse. The malware developers realized
early on that if they want to get their
software on your computer, they need to
be as invisible as possible. And one of
the best ways to get onto your system is
to avoid the anti virus and anti-malware
scanner completely. One very common way
to do this in the past was through the
use of a rootkit. The name root in
rootkit describes the super user account
that you would find in Unix or Linux. A
rootkit embeds itself as part of the
core operating system. And because it's
running as the OS itself, it's able to
hide itself from anti virus and
anti-malware scanners. This also makes
the root kit invisible to the operating
system itself. If it can hide itself
from the scanners, it can easily hide
itself from process explorer or task
manager. This makes it very difficult to
remove from your system because it's
difficult to first identify that it's
running on your computer at all.
Fortunately, we addressed the problem of
rootkits when we created the UEFI BIOS.
This is a very standard basic input
output system that we're using on almost
all of our modern computers today.
There's a feature within the UEFI BIOS
called secure boot. Secure boot will
examine the signature of your operating
system, and if anything has changed with
your core system files, it will not boot
your OS. This has effectively stopped
rootkits from being able to run on our
modern operating systems. There are a
number of scanners that will look for
changes with your operating system and
try to identify cases where rootkits may
have embedded themselves within your OS.
Many anti virus and anti-malware
scanners have also included a rootkit
scanner as part of their basic anti
virus engine. Every rootkit tends to be
a little bit different. So if you have
identified a rootkit on a system, you
may want to get a remover that is
specific to that type of rootkit. And
ultimately using a system with a UEFI
BIOS that has secure boot enabled and
combining that with a modern operating
system effectively limits the scope of a
rootkit on those systems.
Just like an actual virus, a computer
virus needs a human being to be able to
run an application to replicate that
virus from one computer to another. This
might be a program that you've
downloaded from the internet and when
you click on that program, you've now
started the virus running on your
computer. And that virus may be
communicating across the network. Or you
may be moving that virus from one system
to another using some type of USB drive
or other portable storage system. Some
viruses are very quiet when they run.
It's difficult to even know that a
system may be infected with a type of
virus, but some viruses use lots of
resources on the computer, slow
everything down, and make it very
apparent that something else is
happening with that computer. There are
thousands and thousands of new viruses
discovered every week. And it's always
important to keep your anti virus and
anti-malware software updated with the
latest set of virus definitions.
If you ever feel that your computer is
watching you, it may be because there's
spyw wear on your system. Spyware is
malware that is watching what you do and
is either reacting to things that you're
clicking on or it's documenting all of
the things that you're doing on your
system. So, it might be a Trojan horse
that ultimately has the malware that
begins spying on us on our own computer.
Some spyware embeds itself in your
browser. It monitors your surfing
habits, documents all of the websites
you go to, and is able to report all of
that information back to the attacker.
Some spyware will watch everything you
type into your keyboard. We refer to
this type of malware as a key logger.
The key logger is watching everything
you type in onto your computer and
storing that information. So this might
be the URLs you type in to get to a
website or it may be the usernames and
the passwords that you use to log into
your bank account. These key loggers
will commonly collect all of these
keystrokes on your computer and then
once or twice a day it will send that
keystroke information back to the
attacker. This obviously creates a
number of security challenges because
there's no encryption between you and
the keyboard. Every key press you make,
every word that you type, and anything
else that's input into your computer is
stored for analysis later. And these key
loggers very often go beyond just
logging your keystrokes. They might also
log mouse movements. They might capture
screenshots and take anything else that
you're doing and provide that
information to the attacker. Here's what
a key logger looks like when it's
running. I have started up on my
computer a key logger called the dark
comet remote access Trojan or a RAT. It
is now watching all of the keys that I
type in on my computer. So I started up
a copy of Notepad. I typed in the words
username colon professor Messer and
password not a real password. You'll
notice the key logger has captured all
of this information inside the key
logger application. I started up
notepad. I typed in the word username
colon professor messer. I typed in
password colon not. I did a space and
then a backspace and then a real
password. On the screen, of course, it
looks like all one word. And then you
can see I hit the escape key and all of
this information was saved so that the
attacker could examine it later.
Ransomware is one of the newer forms of
malware and it's a type of malware that
has become prevalent in recent years.
Ransomware operates by encrypting all of
your private documents and then it holds
those documents for ransom. Once you pay
the attacker, they provide you with a
decryption key and you can gain access
to your documents again. So anything
that's on your system that you might
have saved is now encrypted and
unavailable to you. If you don't have
backups, then you have no way to recover
any of this important data.
Interestingly enough, with ransomware,
the underlying operating system is
usually not encrypted because the
attacker needs that operating system to
run. They'll usually have a message pop
up on your screen that tells you exactly
what you need to do if you want to gain
access to those files again. The
attacker knows that they're using very
strong encryption methods to be able to
protect your files. And there's no way
to regain access again unless you can
somehow get your hands on that
decryption key.
Many viruses are written just like any
other application that would run in your
operating system. So once your OS starts
up, the virus begins as soon as the OS
is available. But some attackers have
found a way to embed their malware
within the bootloadader of the operating
system. So before the OS can even start,
the malware has already begun its
process. This is another case where
secure boot can really help prevent this
type of malware from executing. Secure
boot will check all of our bootloadaders
as we're starting up our system. And if
anything has changed with the signature
of that bootloadader, secure boot will
not boot your system and will prevent
that malware from running.
Many types of cryptocurrency require
some type of work to be done to be able
to process additional cryptocurrency.
For that reason, many crypto miners will
have multiple systems using the maximum
CPU so that they can run through these
very complex mathematical equations in
the hopes of finding some additional
cryptocurrency. The more computers you
can have doing all of this crypto
mining, the more money you could
possibly make. And malware writers know
that they could write malware to embed
onto other people's computers just so
they can run through these mathematical
equations in the hopes of making more
cryptocurrency. Some of these malicious
crypto miners will run as JavaScript on
a web page. So you visit a website and
you'll suddenly notice that your CPU is
spiked. Or you might accidentally click
a link in an email or download software
as part of a Trojan horse and now there
is a malicious crypto miner that's
running as an executable on your system.
Many of these crypto miners will often
use most of your CPU resources. So it's
usually very obvious that something is
not quite right in your operating
system. Fortunately, most anti virus and
anti-malware software will look for this
type of software and remove it from your
system.
A somewhat disturbing type of malware is
referred to as stalker wear. This is
software that's designed to watch where
you're going and what you're doing and
it's designed to report that information
back to the attacker. This is software
that you can download from the internet
from many different companies. And
usually it's software that is installed
by someone that you happen to know. You
can think of this as the worst kind of
spyw wear. It's watching everything you
do and everywhere you're going. This
might collect screenshots from your
computer, identify where you happen to
be based on your GPS coordinates. It
might be listening in to your microphone
or recording information from your
camera. This is also a very common
technique that countries will use to
surveil other countries and try to find
out what may be happening over the
border. But the software is not
invisible. And if you're using the right
anti-malware or anti virus software, you
can probably identify stalkerware
running on your system and be able to
remove it completely.
In a lot of the descriptions of malware
so far, we've described the process of
downloading a file into our computer,
clicking on that file, and running that
program. But there is a type of malware
that does not store any files on your
system. If you were to perform a file
scan with your anti virus scanner, you
would not be able to find any instances
of a fileless virus. That's because this
virus is never installing itself as part
of the operating system or saving itself
into a particular directory. It's always
going to run in the memory of your
system. And once that virus is done, it
simply disappears completely. Like most
viruses, of course, this fileless virus
starts with the user beginning the
process. This might be the user clicking
on something on a website or inside of
an email message. That click begins to
take advantage of a vulnerability
associated with a piece of software. In
previous years, we would see this with
Flash, but you could also find this with
Java or simply with a Windows
vulnerability. Once the fileless virus
has found that vulnerability in Windows,
it can now tell PowerShell to start up
and begin running a particular script.
Notice so far that we still have not
stored any files to the file system and
everything we've done so far is running
in the memory of your computer. From
there, the program inside of your RAM
can do anything that a normal virus
would do. It may be exfiltrating data
from your system, encrypting and
damaging files that you might have,
deleting information from your storage
drive, or anything else that a virus
might want to do. And before it
finishes, it might add an auto start to
your registry. so that the next time you
start your system, it goes through the
entire process again. This is another
good reason why you might want to have
anti-malware software that runs in real
time with your operating system so that
it can stop a fileless virus from
executing inside of your RAM.
Some viruses are not so much malicious
as they are annoying. We refer to this
type of virus as a potentially unwanted
program or a pup. This type of virus is
still identified by anti virus and
anti-malware. So if you're running the
latest signatures, then you'll be able
to identify and eradicate any of these
pups. Very often, this unwanted software
is something that you're installing
along with something else. But once it
gets on your system and begins running,
it can now perform a number of different
functions. For example, it's very common
for this puptype software to be
associated with ADW wear or some type of
process for making money by showing you
ads on the screen. If you've ever seen
someone's browser that has a very large
toolbar with a lot of icons on it and
you can't seem to get rid of it, it's
probably a potentially unwanted program.
I've also seen pups that disguise
themselves as backup utilities, but what
it really is doing is showing you
advertising. And if you're doing some
type of search inside of your browser
and you hit enter, but instead of going
to Google, you end up at some other very
unusual search engine page, then you're
probably running a potentially unwanted
program that is hijacked your browser
and presenting you with a different set
of results. Here's an actual scan that I
ran on one of my computers that
identified a large number of potentially
unwanted programs. Some of these are
named multiple times in this list,
applications such as Conduit or Spigot.
But you can see that one is called My PC
Backup, which pretends to be a backup
program, but in reality doesn't do
backup very well and is very good at
showing you advertising. To prevent
these potentially unwanted programs from
running on your computer, make sure that
you always keep your anti virus and your
anti-malware signatures up to date.