When you're troubleshooting malware
problems, you may find that your
operating system is difficult to use or
it may not start at all. But there may
be times when you need to recover
certain files from this system before
wiping it completely to remove the
malware. In order to gain access to the
operating system, you might want to try
using the Windows recovery environment.
This provides you with a command prompt
that allows you access to the file
system before it loads the Windows
operating system. This is a powerful
prompt that gives you full access to all
of the files and the entire operating
system. So, you have to be very careful
about the things that you're changing in
the Windows recovery environment. From
this command prompt, you can start or
stop different services. You can modify
what starts up when the operating system
begins. And you could certainly run any
type of uninstall application from this
command prompt to remove the malicious
software. This is one of the reasons why
we spend so much time in this course
talking not only about the graphical
Windows system but also the things that
you can do at a command prompt from this
Windows recovery environment. We can
copy files, rename information or move
these files to a different part of the
file system. We can enable or disable
services or modify what applications are
starting when you launch the Windows
operating system. Or if you are having
problems with the file system, the boot
sector, or any other part of the startup
process, you can modify, troubleshoot,
and make changes to that part of the
operating system from this Windows
recovery environment. If you have the
installation media you use to install
Windows, you can boot to that
installation media and start the Windows
recovery environment. Or if you're
already in Windows, you can choose to
restart. And while you choose the
restart option, hold down the shift key.
When the system starts back up, it will
launch the recovery environment options.
If you're running Windows 10, you can go
to the settings app. This is under
update and security. There's a recovery
option, and you can choose advanced
startup and click the button to restart.
Now, if you're running Windows 11, it's
very similar. You still go to the system
app. You go to the recovery option under
advanced startup, and you choose the
option to restart. Now,
here's my Windows 11 desktop. We'll go
down to the search and we'll type set
tin and then it finishes up with the
settings app right at the top. Once we
start the settings app, if we scroll
down just a bit, you'll see the option
for recovery. If we click the recovery
option, there's a link for advanced
startup and we can click the button to
restart now. A dialogue box appears
reminding us that we are going to
restart the system right now. So, if you
have anything that you need to save,
make sure you do that before clicking
the restart now button. Windows then
goes through the standard restart
process and everything at this point
looks relatively normal. Here's the
Windows recovery environment for Windows
11. From here, we can continue to
Windows 11, turn off your PC, use a
device, or in this case, we will choose
troubleshoot. From here, we can reset
this PC that lets you keep or remove
your personal files and reinstalls the
Windows operating system. But in this
case, we're going to choose advanced
options. Here are the options for
startup repair, the installation of
updates, startup settings, any firmware
settings for the UEFI BIOS, and the
option that we're going to use, which is
command prompt. Clicking on that puts
you at the command prompt. And from
here, you have full access to the
Windows operating system.
Over the last number of years, our
anti-malware and anti virus software has
been evolving to make our systems more
secure while at the same time the number
of threats continues to scale upward.
One of these improvements is the
endpoint detection and response software
or EDR. This is software that can detect
malicious code without specifically
using a signature. It performs
behavioral analysis. It does machine
learning. It might even monitor all of
the processes on your system and if it
identifies anything that does not look
normal, it will stop that software from
running. This also collects information
about the software that it's seeing so
that you can perform a root cause
analysis to determine how that software
originally got on the system. And of
course, it provides you with tools you
can use to respond to any particular
threat. It can isolate this system
automatically, quarantine the threat
that it has found and automatically roll
back to a previous configuration. This
allows your users to keep operating the
systems continue to be up and running,
but in the background, we're still
providing security to prevent this type
of malware from executing.
Many organizations will have a third
party manage this process of monitoring
for malicious software. In that case,
this third-party EDR service is referred
to as a managed detection and response
or MDR. You'll often see an MDR provided
by a managed security service provider
or MSSP. They are responsible for
monitoring all of your systems, and if
they detect any threats to these
systems, they react on your behalf. The
MSSP often has professionals on staff
that understand the intricacies of
malicious software and they can use that
knowledge across all of their different
customers systems. This allows your
in-house security team to manage the
more important security issues while
third party takes care of the detection
and response of any malicious software.
EDR and MDR were created to focus on the
individual devices. But as we all know,
today's malware can affect more than
just a single computer and often
involves many different aspects of the
infrastructure. To bring all of those
different devices and endpoints into a
complete view of what's happening on
your network, we've created extended
detection and response or XDR. Not only
are we now watching individual
endpoints, we're now watching the
traffic traversing the network to be
able to identify malicious software at a
completely different level. This also
begins collecting data from all of these
different points and bringing them back
to one central database where we can
perform correlation analysis. So now we
can examine and correlate between
endpoints, network data, and cloud data
to be able to identify where this
malicious software might be and how to
prevent it in the future.
If you're managing a relatively small
network or a network that is just your
systems at home, you're probably just
using anti virus and anti-malware
software. These usually run as real-time
options on your system. So, it is
constantly watching everything that
you're doing. And if you happen to
download something that is deemed to be
malicious, it will be identified
immediately by this real-time scanner.
We are starting to see enhancements to a
number of anti virus and anti-malware
software suites where they're able to
identify malicious actions that are
outside the scope of a signature. So if
there is something occurring on your
system that clearly was created because
of something malicious, your anti virus
and anti-malware software can stop it in
its tracks.
Email is a very popular vector for
attacks. We can send information in an
email message to get someone to click on
a malicious link or maybe we attach the
malicious software to the email message
itself. For that reason, many
organizations will monitor all of their
email transactions and look for any type
of malicious software or malicious
information that is contained within
these email messages. Most networks will
have a mail gateway where all of their
mail is sent. So, anything from outside
the internet that is inbound to your
users generally will pass through a
firewall and then to an internal mail
gateway. Once that mail is scanned and
everything is approved, it can then be
forwarded on to an internal mail server
and distributed to your endusers. Many
organizations have also moved that mail
gateway into the cloud. So now we have a
powerful cloud-based email gateway that
is collecting information from hundreds
or even thousands of different email
systems and is able to find that
malicious software much easier and be
able to react in a centralized
cloud-based system.
Many organizations will also enable
Windows Defender firewall or some type
of third-party firewall on all of their
endpoint devices. This personal firewall
will monitor all network communication
in and out of the system and will
identify anything that is not allowed to
communicate to that endpoint. This is
especially important if malware does
find a way to get installed onto that
operating system. Many malware variants
will attempt to communicate outside of
your network to the internet where there
might be a command and control server.
This type of softwarebased firewall can
monitor for any of those transactions
and stop that communication before it
leaves that endpoint. Most operating
systems will include a softwarebased
firewall, and it's always a good idea to
enable it and have it running all the
time. This allows you to have a process
that is constantly watching the network
communication over your network. And if
there is unexpected network traffic from
malware or from any source, the personal
firewall will identify it, alert, and
then block it from communicating.
One type of attack that is extremely
difficult to identify through electronic
means is social engineering. This is one
of the reasons that fishing attacks are
so successful because they're able to
circumvent our technology and attack the
people within our organization directly.
This is why many organizations have
extensive training on fishing. They want
to be sure that all of their employees
know exactly what this threat might be
and how to react if they identify that
threat on their system. To see if their
end users really do remember their
training, many organizations will test
their users by sending a fishing email
and see if anybody happens to click on
those internal links. This is something
that can be easily reported on. And if
someone does happen to click a link and
provide their private information, it
may be time for some additional
training.
Training for security concerns can be
more than just looking for fishing
attacks. It can be for any type of
attack that might occur to your systems.
And in-user training can take many
different forms as well. We can
certainly have one-on-one training where
one person is explaining to another
individual this type of security issue
and how to resolve it. Or we might have
posters and signs so anytime someone
walks into the building they can see
information on how to better protect
their system. Some organizations will
have a message board or internal forums
which may also be a good way to inform
your user community of any urgent
threats. This might also be included
with a login message. So when somebody
pops open a login screen, they'll be
able to see the message of the day and
know what the important concerns might
be regarding IT security. And most
organizations will have an internet or
some type of centralized web services.
And this is also a great place to store
documentation and provide additional
details on IT security.
Although many people will go through a
process of trying to remove malware from
a system, the only way to be 100% sure
that you have removed all of that
malware is to completely delete that
system and restore it from a known good
backup or a known good image. If you do
have a known good backup, this is a very
quick way to restore, especially if it's
in an image form where you can simply
have the entire system wiped and then
restore it with a complete duplicate of
what was there originally. Restoring
from backup is a relatively fast way to
get a system back up and running, but
you are limited to the last date that
you made that backup. So, if the backup
was made 24 hours ago, you might be
missing some of the work that you've
done in that last 24 hours. One of the
slowest forms of restoring a system
would be a manual restoration where you
manually install Windows and then go
through the process of manually
installing any applications required by
that user. And the way that many
organizations will perform this
restoration is by using an image.
They've created a predefined
configuration for that system that they
can easily copy down that includes the
operating system and all required
applications. Since many organizations
will keep their user data on a network
share, deleting everything on a local
system and restoring from an image
provides you a way to get that system
back up and running as quickly as
possible.