In this video, we're going to describe a
series of steps that will allow you to
remove malware from a system. In the
vast majority of cases, this will not be
the process you use to actually remove
malware. That's because even after going
through the steps in this video, it is
possible for malware to still be on that
system. You're never going to be 100%
sure that you removed all of the malware
from that computer. The way that most
organizations address a malware
infection is to delete everything on
that system and then reimage or replace
it with known good software. So if the
best practice is to completely delete
everything on a system and start over,
why are we discussing the process of
removing malware and keeping everything
intact? That's because you will
occasionally run into a system that
doesn't boot properly, but you still
need the important documents that may be
stored on that hard drive. If you were
to delete everything on that system, you
would also be deleting those files. So,
this removal process should take you
through the steps that will get your
system running just well enough for you
to remove those important documents.
Once you've been able to recover those
documents, it probably then would be a
best practice to delete everything on
that system and restore from a known
good image.
The first step is to recognize the
symptoms that could indicate that
malware has been installed on your
computer. Sometimes this is very obvious
where the message says operation did not
complete successfully because the file
contains a virus or potentially unwanted
software. or a message may come from
your Windows security that says threats
have been found and Microsoft Defender
anti virus found some threats. Click to
get more details. But often it's not
quite this obvious. It might be
something as simple as the system is
taking a bit longer to boot or perhaps
it's running a bit more sluggish than it
normally does. Or perhaps you're getting
a message in an application that is an
unusual error message but doesn't
directly tie back to any type of
malware. All of these could be symptoms
of malware. So, it's always a good idea
to perform some additional research and
find out more about what could be
causing this problem on your computer.
If you do believe that malware has
infected a system, it's time to take
some action. This step too would be to
quarantine this infected system away
from any other devices on your network.
Malware can find its way across the
network, so you should disconnect the
network connections or disable those
network links as soon as possible. It's
also very easy to move malware between
systems using a USB drive or some other
type of removable media. And at this
point, many people believe that they
should back up the system to be able to
restore information later. But if this
system really is infected with malware,
you don't want to back up that malware
just to restore it later.
Another useful function of Windows is
the system restore capability. This
allows you to move your system
configuration back to a previous date
and time. And if you're trying to remove
malware from a system, you would think
that that would be an easy fix. You
simply change your system to the same
configurations you had last week, and
that should get rid of the malware. But
the malware authors have already thought
of that particular occasion. So when
they infect your system, they will also
infect your restore points. So, you can
still go back in time to a previous
restore point, but you'll effectively be
restoring the malware back to your
system. If you're in a corporate
environment, you may find that the
system restore capability has already
been disabled. But if you're using
Windows at home or you have a computer
where system protection is enabled,
you'll want to disable that capability.
When you disable system restore, it
completely deletes all of your previous
restore points. And if any malware is in
those restore points, it will also be
deleted. This will be a temporary
configuration and later on in the
malware removal steps we'll discuss when
we would want to reenable system
restore.
Now we need to fix the malware issue
that we have. One of the things we can
do is to remove any files that we have
clearly identified as malicious. Some
malware can be identified by an
anti-malware scanner. You click a button
to remove those files and the malware
has been removed from your computer. If
the malware was identified in a
real-time scan, then those files were
probably already deleted and moved to a
special location on your system drive to
quarantine the files. This keeps the
files available for administrators to be
able to perform additional research, but
it doesn't allow the user access to
those infected files. But if you've ever
done any type of malware removal, you
know that it very often isn't as simple
as deleting a single file and rebooting.
Very often malware embeds itself within
many different points inside the
operating system making it extremely
difficult to completely remove.
In many cases, you will use anti virus
or anti-malware software to identify and
then remove the malware from the system.
In order for your anti virus software to
identify the malware, it needs to have
the latest set of signatures. You also
want to make sure that you're running
the latest anti virus engine so that
it's up to date with the latest version
of software. Once you've updated both
your engine and updated the signatures,
you can begin the process of removing
this malware. Often this is an automatic
process. You simply tell the
anti-malware software to run a scan of
your system and if it finds anything, it
will remove it from your computer. On
most systems, these updates are
performed automatically. So, you may
find that the anti virus engine and all
of the signatures are already up to
date, but you might find on some systems
that the anti virus updates have been
set to manual. Very commonly, anti virus
signatures are updated multiple times a
day. So, setting a system to a manual
update is almost pointless considering
all of the changes that occur on a daily
basis. And if your system is infected
with malware, you may find that
attempting to update the signatures or
update the anti virus engine will fail
because the malware is blocking your
system from performing those updates. It
may require you to manually download
these files on a separate system, put
them on a USB drive, boot the system
into a recovery mode, and manually copy
the files and updates.
If the malware is affecting the bootup
process of your computer, you might be
able to boot into a less capable mode
known as safe mode. This will load a
barebones operating system that allows
you to at least get to the Windows
desktop and be able to change files or
delete information from your drive. On
rare occasions, this might also prevent
the malware from running, which might
give you some additional options during
the recovery process. And if this
malware has created a problem on your
system, you might not even be able to
boot into safe mode. In that case, you
might want to take advantage of the
Windows pre-installation environment or
WinP. This is the environment used for
the Windows recovery console where you
can boot your system onto a command
prompt and then be able to change the
file system from there. You can also
create your own Windows pre-installation
environment using the Windows assessment
and deployment kit or ADK. And if the
pre-installation environment is not able
to find your Windows installation, then
you might have to repair boot records or
modify additional information in the
operating system.
At this point, you should be able to
boot the system, gain access to the file
system, and be able to transfer over any
important documents. At this point, it's
time to delete everything and start over
from the beginning. We often refer to
this as a reimage process or a reinstall
process. Most organizations will have
separate images for the hardware that
they use and so they can delete
everything, apply the image to that
system, and in a matter of minutes have
that computer back up and running. This
not only installs the Windows operating
system, but all of the appropriate
drivers, files, applications, and
anything else needed for that company.
This is also one of the reasons that we
often redirect folders or require
individuals to save their documents to a
network drive. This way you can delete
everything on a local computer and not
have to worry that you're deleting
important documents.
Now we're back up and running and we're
virus free. Now we need to set
configuration options so that this
problem doesn't occur again. It's always
a good idea to check if your anti virus
software is running in a real time mode
so it's scanning everything going
through your system in real time. But
it's also a good idea to perform
periodic scans. This will check for any
files that may have been added or files
that you aren't directly accessing
through the real time scanner. Some
antivirus software is a built-inuler for
configuring anti virus updates to the
engine and to the signatures. But if
your anti virus software doesn't support
that feature, you might need to add a
task into taskuler to ensure that you're
always getting the latest signatures
installed onto your computer. And of
course, it's always a good idea to check
to see if your operating system update
process is also configured. In Windows,
you'll want to check Windows update and
make sure that it's also configured to
download and install any new patches.
I mentioned earlier that we had to
delete all of our restore points because
all of them were most likely infected
with malware. Now that we've completely
deleted everything on our system
restored from a known good image, we can
make sure that our system restore is
enabled. Again, you want to check the
system properties under the system
protection tab and make sure that the
restore settings are set to turn on
system protection. And since we've just
turned system restore back on, you might
want to click the button to create a
restore point right now for the drives
that have system protection turned on.
This will ensure that you've got a good
configuration that you could move back
to if you ever need to go back in time
with your system config.
Sometimes malware can get onto our
systems without any type of user
intervention. But often it's the users
that run the software that infects their
systems to begin with. And there are
some best practices your users should
know about what to click, when to click
it, and how to notify when they think
that something may have gone wrong. You
might want to have one-on-one training
with that individual and talk to them
about IT security and how they can keep
this system protected going forward. You
might also want to have a broader
campaign where you might use posters and
signs. You might post these right
outside the elevator so that when it
opens up, everybody can see those
posters on the wall. Or it might be a
message board posting in the breakroom.
So, if you have a board in the breakroom
that has information and announcements,
this might also be a good place to talk
about anti virus and anti-malware best
practices. Since everyone also has to
visit the login page, this is also a
good place to put a message of the day.
Sometimes this is information about
systems that might be unavailable during
different time frames, or it might
include a tip or trick on how to keep
your system safe. And almost every
organization has an internet page. This
is a perfect place to keep all of your
documentation, information on who to
contact, and details about anti virus
and anti-malware best practices.